A Guide to the Papers of Dr. Carolyn Rhodes, 1965-2003
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of Dr. Carolyn Rhodes 1924-1926, 1965-2003
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
79
7 Hollinger document cases, 2.9 linear feet
Rhodes, Carolyn, Dr.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
All materials were donated by Dr. Carolyn H. Rhodes.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. Carolyn H. Rhodes was born Carolyn Hodgson on May 16, 1925 in Birmingham, Alabama. Her parents were Lester Rhodes Hodgson and Dolly Griffin Hodgson. Dr. Rhodes has Bachelor of Arts degrees in Psychology and English from the University of Alabama, a Master of Arts degree in Psychology from Columbia University and a Master of Arts degree in English from the University of Kentucky. She earned her Ph.D. in English in 1965 from the University of Kentucky. While in college, Dr. Rhodes administered psychometric tests for the Veterans Administration in Lexington, Kentucky and worked as an Editorial Assistant for Railway Age Magazine. She was a Haggin teaching fellow for nine semesters, from 1957-1963, and an instructor of English Language Orientation for Indonesian students from 1964-1965.
Dr. Rhodes moved to Virginia and began as an Assistant Professor at Old Dominion University (then Old Dominion College) in 1965. She became an Associate Professor in 1969 and a Professor of English in 1978. During her tenure at Old Dominion University, Dr. Rhodes worked as the Principle Investigator for the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) Pilot Grant in Women's Studies. The grant, which ran from May 1977 to August 1978, helped establish the Women's Studies program at ODU, the first of its kind in Virginia. Dr. Rhodes was also a co-founder of the Friends of Women's Studies organization, established in 1985 to provide monetary support to keep Women's Studies alive. From September 1982 to July 1983, Dr. Rhodes was a Fulbright Lecturer in American Literature at Babes-Bolyai University in Romania. She received a second Fulbright to lecturer in American Literature at Peking University in Bejing, from September 1986 to August 1987
Dr. Rhodes has two children, Richard (b. 1949) and Babette (b. 1951). She and her husband, Ernest Rhodes, reside in Virginia.
Chronology
Date of Birth: May 16, 1925
Bachelor of Arts in Psychology, University of Alabama: 1945
Bachelor of Arts in English, University of Alabama: 1945
Master of Arts in Psychology, Columbia University: 1947
Master of Arts in English, University of Kentucky: 1959
Doctorate in English, University of Kentucky: 1965
Assistant Professor, Old Dominion University: 1965
Associate Professor, Old Dominion University: 1969
Principle Investigator, NEH Pilot Grant, Women's Studies: 1977-1978
Professor of English, Old Dominion University: 1978
Fulbright Lecturer, Romania: 1982-1983
Co-founder, Friends of Women's Studies: 1985
Fulbright Lecturer, Bejing: 1986-1987
Scope and Content
The Papers of Dr. Carolyn H. Rhodes date from 1965 to 2003 and contain documents from Dr. Rhodes' academic and professional career. Most of the materials in the collection relate to Dr. Rhodes career at Old Dominion University in the English and Women's Studies departments, as well as her continuing activism on behalf of women and their status at ODU.
Index Terms
Rhodes, Carolyn, Dr.; Old Dominion University. Dept. of English; Old Dominion University. Dept. of Women's Studies; Women's studies--Virginia--Norfolk
Contents List
- Dr. Carolyn Rhodes 1965-1990
  This series contains materials specific to Dr. Carolyn Rhodes including a biographical sketch and her academic resume.
  Alphabetical by topic
  - Academic Resume 1990 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Biographical Sketch 1965 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - List of Publications by Carolyn Rhodes 1989 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Support Letters for Awarding Carolyn Rhodes Emeritus Status on Her Retirement May 1990 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Women's Caucus 1990-1993
  This series contains speeches made by Dr. Carolyn Rhodes at Women's Caucus events and her personal notes on the Caucus.
  Chronological
  - Remarks Before ODU Women's Caucus -- First Lifetime Achievement Award (Velma Powell) 1990 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Speech as Part of the 20th Women's Caucus Celebration 1993 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Personal Notes Toward Women's Caucus History undated (Box-folder 1:7)
- Women's Studies 1976-2003
  This series is broken into six sub-series.
  - Course Materials 1985-2000
    This sub-series contains materials from Women's Studies courses including course descriptions, syllabi, coursepaks, and reading lists.
    Alphabetical by course name
    - Changing Perspectives for Women Spring 1986 (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Changing Perspectives for Women Spring 1988 (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Feminist Utopias (WMSTS 395) 1986 (Box-folder 1:10)
    - Life Narratives Spring 2000 (Box-folder 1:11)
    - When Women Tell (WS 395) Fall 1985 (Box-folder 1:12)
    - Women and Their Literature in 20th Century China (WS 495) Fall 1989 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Faculty 1988
    This sub-series contains information on Women's Studies faculty. Currently there is only one faculty member represented, Dr. Ellen Lewin, Director of Women's Studies in 1988.
    - Dr. Ellen Lewin, New Director of Women's Studies 1988 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Grants and Scholarships 1976-2003
    This sub-series contains information on grants and scholarships related to Women's Studies. Included are materials on the Women's Studies scholarships in honor of Carolyn Rhodes and Nancy Bazin, and the National Endowment for the Humanities grant that helped establish the first Women's Studies courses at ODU.
    - NEH Pilot Grant in Women's Studies July 1976 (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Feminist Educational Trust Fund 1978-1980 (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Memorandum of Understanding Endowed Scholarship 1998 (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Endowments 2003 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Events 1979-1997
    This sub-series contains materials related to Women's Studies events. Included are lectures and lecture series; conferences; and other informational events related to women and Women's Studies.
    - Guest Lecture: The American Woman's Quest for Identity 6 February 1979 (Box-folder 1:19)
    - Women Artists from the Renaissance to Today 13 February 1979 (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Guest Lecture: Women's Lives Views from Within 1 March 1985 (Box-folder 1:21)
    - Virginia Beach Public Library Lecture Series: The Contemporary Southern Woman 1985 (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Work in Progress VII: A Conference on Feminist Scholarship in Hampton Roads and 20th Anniversary Celebration of ODU Women's Studies Program 6-7 June 1997 (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Reflections on Our Lives undated (Box-folder 1:24)
    - What's in the Cards for Women's Studies? undated (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Promotional Materials 1980-1997
    This sub-series contains brochures, flyers, and announcements. These are mainly related to courses and course offerings.
    Alphabetical
    - Course Brochure (Women's Studies) Spring 1984 (Box-folder 1:26)
    - Course Listings Flyer (Women's Center) Spring 1980 (Box-folder 1:27)
    - Course Offerings flyer (Women's Studies) 1997 (Box-folder 1:28)
    - Flyers and Announcements 1987-1988 (Box-folder 1:29)
    - Why Women's Studies? Brochure (Box-folder 1:30)
  - Studies and Reports 1974-1978
    This sub-series contains studies and reports relating to Women's Studies and to Women's Status at ODU.
    - Questionnaire on Women's Status at ODU and Results April 1974 (Box-folder 1:31)
    - Questionnaire on Women's Status at ODU and Results May 1975 (Box-folder 1:32)
    - Final Grant Report, Undergraduate Women's Studies Program 1977-1978 (Box-folder 1:33)
    - Final Grant Report, Undergraduate Women's Studies Program 1977-1978, copy (Box-folder 1:34)
- Other Courses 1972-1989
  Series IV relates to courses other than Women's Studies. It is composed of four sub-series.
  - Asian Studies 1987-1989
    This sub-series contains materials related to the Asian Studies Department. Included are materials related to position openings in this department in 1987-88, and a program where eleven faculty members, including Dr. Carolyn Rhodes, went to East Asia for a study tour.
    - Institute of Asian Studies 1987-1988 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Faculty Development Seminar in East Asian Studies, ODU/TCC 1989 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - English 1972-1984
    This sub-series contains materials related to English courses that Dr. Carolyn Rhodes taught.
    - The Literature of Technology, Comparative Literature 498 Spring 1972 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - English 396-O, Spring 1978 and English 560 Spring 1977 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Science Fiction - Science Fact, English 320M Spring 1980 (Box-folder 2:5)
    - American Autobiography, English 691 Fall 1984 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Utopian Studies 1976-1985
    This sub-series contains materials related to Utopian Studies courses at ODU. Included is information on credit and non-credit courses, as well as a conference held in the Fall of 1985.
    - Free University Course in Science Fiction Summer 1976 (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Quests for Utopia 1981 (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Conference of Utopian Studies 27-29 September 1985 (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Utopian Thought in Fiction undated (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Various 1977-1978
    This sub-series contains materials related to a Humanities course, "On Death and Dying," taught by Dr. Carolyn Rhodes in 1977 and 1978.
    - On Death and Dying, Humanities 395 Fall 1977, Fall 1978 (Box-folder 2:11)
- Speeches and Presentations 1978-1997
  This series contains speeches and presentations given by Dr. Carolyn Rhodes at various workshops and events. Speeches relate to mainly to women's topics.
  - Godwin's Variation on Themes of Motherhood for Modern Language Association Conference 1978 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Women Writers and the American Dream Given at Various Chinese Universities 1986-1987 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Women Writers and Views of American Life Given in China 1986-1987 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Poems by the Sea for the Algonquin Garden Club 4 January 1985 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - 20th Anniversary Memories for Women's Studies Banquet 1997 (Box-folder 2:16)
- Publications 1924-1926, 1965-1995
  This series is broken into seven sub-series.
  - Published Material by Carolyn Rhodes 1971-1984
    This sub-series contains book chapters written by Dr. Carolyn Rhodes, as well as information on books she edited.
    - Intelligence Testing in Utopia in Extrapolation: A Journal of Science Fiction and Fantasy 1971 (Box-folder 2:17)
    - First Person Female American 1980 (Box-folder 2:18)
    - New Women at Old Dominion in Stepping Off the Pedastal 1982 (Box-folder 2:19)
    - Method in Her Madness in Women and Utopia 1983 (Box-folder 2:20)
    - Your Faces, O My Sisters! Your Faces Filled of Light in Aurora: Beyond Equality 1983 (Box-folder 2:21)
    - Gail Godwin and the Ideal of Southern Womanhood in Women Writers of the Contemporary South 1984 (Box-folder 2:22)
  - Annotated Books 1926, 1971-1992
    This sub-series contains books annotated with notes written by Dr. Carolyn Rhodes.
    Alphabetical by title
    - Encounters with Chinese Writers 1984 (Box-folder 3:1)
    - First Person Singular 1973 (Box-folder 3:2)
    - Gail Godwin's Stories (translated into Chinese) 1992 (Box-folder 3:3)
    - Herland: A Lost Feminist Utopian Novel 1979 (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Idylls of the King 1926 (Box-folder 3:5)
    - The Kin of Ata are Waiting for You 1971 (Box-folder 3:6)
    - Lilies and Other Stories 1985 (Box-folder 4:1)
    - Love Must Not Be Forgotten 1987 (Box-folder 4:2)
    - Peaceable Kingdoms: An Anthology of Utopian Writings 1971 (Box-folder 4:3)
    - The United States and China 1976 (Box-folder 4:4)
    - We 1924 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Journals 1981-1990
    This sub-series contains journals related to Women's Studies and Related to Utopian Studies.
    - Synthesis, Published by the University of Pittsburgh, Women's Center 1981-1982 (Box-folder 5:1)
    - Utopian Studies 1990 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Newsletters 1970-1989?
    This sub-series contains Women's Studies newsletters from the 1970s and 1980s.
    - Iris: Women's Studies Newsletter, University of Virginia 1970-1989 (Box-folder 5:3)
    - Women's Studies Newsletter, A Publication of the Feminist Press and the National Women's Studies Association 1977 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Newspaper Articles 1966-1995
    This sub-series contains newspaper articles related to Carolyn Rhodes; the Title IX sex bias hearings; the Affirmative Action office; the Women's Center; the Women's Studies program; and science fiction courses and lectures at ODU.
    - Poetry Program Planned (Dr. Carolyn Meyers), Mace and Crown 4 November 1966 (Box-folder 5:5)
    - ODU Course on Women, Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star 17 February 1972 (Box-folder 5:6)
    - SF and Computers to be Topic of Next Lecture, Unews 13 April 1973 (Box-folder 5:7)
    - ODU p Professor's Life Work to be Published (Ernest Rhodes), Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star 7 March 1973 (Box-folder 5:8)
    - Rhodes Publishes Triumph, Unews 9 March 1973 (Box-folder 5:9)
    - Old-Time Etiquette: Avoid Show of Knowledge, Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star 13 March 1975 (Box-folder 5:10)
    - Science Fiction Goes to College, Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star 14 August 1975 (Box-folder 5:11)
    - Salary and Tenure Compared by Sex, Unews 20 February 1976 (Box-folder 5:12)
    - Survey of Sex Discrimination in Academe Begun, Unews 18 June 1976 (Box-folder 5:13)
    - Hearings on Sex Bias Set, Unews 2 July 1976 (Box-folder 5:14)
    - Is the Question Whether or How Much? (Title X), Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star 15 July 1976 (Box-folder 5:15)
    - Sex Bias Hearings Continue, Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star 16 July 1976 (Box-folder 5:16)
    - President Speaks to Faculty, Outlines Priorities, Unews 26 August 1976 (Box-folder 5:17)
    - Title IX Hearings Move into Final Week, Mace and Crown 27 September 1976 (Box-folder 5:18)
    - ODU Workshop Focuses on Women in Education, The Compass 8 October 1976 (Box-folder 5:19)
    - Women's Center, Faculty Club Sponsor Conference on Women, Unews 8 October 1976 (Box-folder 5:20)
    - Center Opens to Answer Social Needs, Unews 15 October 1976 (Box-folder 5:21)
    - Discrimination at ODU, Mace and Crown 25 October 1976 (Box-folder 5:22)
    - Women's Numbers Increase, Unews 13 January 1977 (Box-folder 5:23)
    - Salary Averages Listed, Unews 18 March 1977 (Box-folder 5:24)
    - Curry Named Director of Affirmative Action, Unews 3 June 1977 (Box-folder 5:25)
    - Dr. Reuben, Consultant for NEH, and Dr. Rhodes Discuss the Newly Created Woman's Studies Program, Unews 1 August 1977 (Box-folder 5:26)
    - Science Fiction Caters to All, Mace and Crown 12 September 1977 (Box-folder 5:27)
    - Arts Reunion Attracts 2,000 for Programs, Unews 6 October 1977 (Box-folder 5:28)
    - Curry Aims to Make Equality a Reality, Unews 21 October 1977 (Box-folder 5:29)
    - Women's Dream Realized (NEH Pilot Grant for Women's Studies), Unews 2 December 1977 (Box-folder 5:30)
    - Faculty Promotions Given, (Carolyn Rhodes), Unews 28 April 1978 (Box-folder 5:31)
    - Women's Center Strives to Help Women Advance, Unews 27 October 1978 (Box-folder 5:32)
    - Autobiography Subject of Tome (First Person Female American), Unews 26 October 1980 (Box-folder 5:33)
    - Capturing a Heroine (A Review of The Scapegoat), Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star 16 November 1980 (Box-folder 5:34)
    - Southern Feminist (Carolyn Rhodes), Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star 10 March 1985 (Box-folder 5:35)
    - Professors Relate Teaching Abroad, Mace and Crown 22 October 1987 (Box-folder 5:36)
    - Exhibit Traces the Career of Local Art Giant Zetlin, Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star 24 December 1995 (Box-folder 5:37)
    - Need for ODU Day Care Cited, Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star undated (Box-folder 5:38)
  - Unpublished Papers 1965-1990
    This sub-series contains notes, abstracts, and other papers written by Dr. Carolyn Rhodes that aren't published in books or journals. These include the abstract for her dissertation and feminist arguments and critiques.
    - Dissertation Abstract and Bibliography 1965 (Box-folder 5:39)
    - Feminist Criticism of Science Fiction 1971-1976 (Box-folder 5:40)
    - The Case for Women's Studies in Higher Education 1990 (Box-folder 5:41)
    - Feminism and Feminist Criticism, a Very Partial Reading List, For Beginners undated (Box-folder 5:42)
  - Other Publications 1973-1988
    This sub-series contains other publications and articles related to Women's Studies and women at ODU. Included are a theatrical play, yearbook excerpt, and a historical booklet on women at ODU.
    - In Celebration: Women at Old Dominion University 1973-1983 (Box-folder 5:43)
    - People are Women Too (Theatrical Play) undated (Box-folder 5:44)
    - Women's Studies Celebrates 10th Anniversary, The Laureate 1987-1988 (Box-folder 5:45)
- Correspondence 1966-1988
  This series contains correspondence written by or to Dr. Carolyn Rhodes. Much of the material is related to furthering women's status at ODU. One notable letter is from the noted American psychologist B.F. Skinner regarding Carolyn Rhodes dissertation.
  - Letter from B.F. Skinner Regarding Dissertation 10 March 1966 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Letter from Carolyn Rhodes to Title IX Committee on Compliance 14 June 1975 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Memo from Carolyn Rhodes Regarding Appointment of Director of Women's Studies 16 May 1978 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Letter from H.K. Meier, Dean of the School of Arts and Letters Regarding Women's Studies Final Report 6 December 1978 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Memo from Allen K. Clark, Vice Provost for Academic Affairs Regarding Faculty Salary Averages 10 December 1978 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Letter from Carolyn Rhodes to Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star Regarding Affirmative Action Policies 3 May 1979 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Correspondence between Carolyn Rhodes and Maggi Curry, Assistant to the President and Director of AA/EEO regarding article on Women's activism at ODU March 1980 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Memo from Carolyn Rhodes regarding Women's Studies Program 14 October 1985 (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Letter from Gail Regarding Mothers and Daughters 1 December 1988 (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Letter from Carolyn Rhodes to Virginian Pilot-Ledger Star Regarding Thanks for Covering Women's Hearings at ODU undated (Box-folder 6:10)
- Title IX 1975-1980
  This series contains material related to the Title IX sex discrimination hearings at ODU during the 1970s, including statistics on salary and tenure differences between women and men at ODU.
  - Title XI: ODU Salary and Tenure 1975 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Title XI: ODU Salary and Tenure 1976 (Box-folder 6:12)
  - Title XI: ODU Salary and Tenure 1979 (Box-folder 6:13)
  - Title XI: ODU Salary and Tenure 1980 (Box-folder 6:14)
- Multimedia 1983-1999
  This series is broken into two sub-series.
  - Photos 1983-1999
    his series contains photos of Dr. Carolyn Rhodes. Material is from the 1980s and 1990s
    - Carolyn Rhodes Receiving Caucus Award Fall 1983 (Box-folder 6:15)
    - Nancy Bazin and Carolyn Rhodes 1990-1999 (Box-folder 6:16)
  - VHS Tapes 1980-1989
    This series contains VHS tapes of lectures on women's concerns.
    - Dr. Carolyn Rhode's Talk on Gail Godwin's A Mother and Two Daughters 1985 (Box-folder 6:17)
    - Fay Zetlin Undated (Box-folder 6:18)
- Awards 1989-1991
  This series contains awards bestowed upon Dr. Carolyn Rhodes for her service to ODU and the community.
  - ODU Service Recognition Award 1989 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Women's Caucus Recognition Award 1989 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - YWCA Winner's Award 1989 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - ODU Service Recognition Award 1990 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Most Inspiring Faculty Award 1989 (Box-folder 7:5)
- Miscellaneous Women's Events 1980-1989?
  This series contains materials related to women's events and lectures that were sponsored by organizations other than ODU Women's Studies, though Women's Studies was likely to have supported and attended these events.
  - Every Woman's Festival 15 February 1980 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Conference on Women in the Year 2000 7-9 April 1988 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Federalist Feminists undated (Box-folder 7:8)